All
right. בוקר טוב. Boker tov. We are, we had a few technical
difficulties, so but now we're hopefully going. We're on the bottom of
מ"א Mem Aleph 41, fifth chapter in מסכת סנהדרין, Masechet Sanhedrin, the
chapter of היו בודקים Hayu Bodkim where we're checking the witnesses. As
we know, we have different systems to check the witnesses. We could
do חקירות chakirot investigations—in which week, in which year, in which day.
We can ask things from the investigations. Do you know this guy?
Have you warned him before? We have דרישות, drishot, we ask them
about him—what did he work in, who is he? And we can
also do בדיקות, bdikot, which are more general questions. There's a lot
of discussions what is the difference between
those—you know, where exactly is the line between all these. So the
fact that we don't know exactly where is the line is okay,
the rabbis debated too. We are going back to pick up from
the משנה mishnah which was on page 40. In the, if we
just want to look at it so that we know what our
גמרא gemara is talking about. On עמוד amud מ' Mem 40, third
line from the wide lines at the end, it says: אחד אומר
בשנים בחודש ואחד אומר בשלשה בחודש עדותן קיימת. Echad omer bishnayim bachodesh
ve'echad omer bishlosha bachodesh, edutan kayemet. We're talking about a discrepancy in
the calendar. What if I say this event took place on the
second of the month and David says, 'Oh no, it actually was
on the third'? The משנה mishnah says to us: עדותן קיימת—this edutan
kayemet is a valid testimony. שזה יודע בעיבורו של חודש וזה אינו
יודע בעיבורו של חודש. shezeh yode'a be'iburo shel chodesh vezeh eino yode'a
be'iburo shel chodesh.
One knows when the new moon happened and one doesn't know. However,
זה אומר בשלשה ואחד אומר בחמשה עדותן בטלה. zeh omer bishlosha ve'echad
omer bachamisha, edutan betela. So if one said it was the third
of the month and the other says of the fifth, their testimony
is not valid anymore. Okay. The גמרא gemara is asking us: עד
כמה? ad kama? How far into the month can we employ this
system that somebody doesn't know which day it is? And we talked
yesterday a little bit after the שיעור shiur that for some of
us, we can go the whole month and not know exactly which
day it is, including me. So the גמרא gemara is going to
discuss what exactly is the issue here. And then just heads up
kind of where we're going, then we'll have a little bit of
a discussion since we're already talking about the month, we'll have a
discussion about the whole issue of ברכת לבנה—like birkat levana when are
we saying the blessing of the moon?—and then conclude a couple of
other things from היו בודקים Hayu Bodkim before proceeding to the next
עמוד, amud, hopefully. Okay. עד כמה? ad kama? How far? אמר רבי
אחא בר חנינא אמר רבי אסי אמר רבי יוחנן: Amar Rabbi Acha
bar Chanina amar Rabbi Assi amar Rabbi Yochanan: עד רובו של חודש.
ad rubo shel chodesh. Most of the month, this system would be
okay that I don't know which day it is. But after like
the middle, I should catch up and know what's going on.
אמר רבא: Amar Rava: אף אנן נמי תנינא. af anan nami tanina.
Also we're taught another
issue: אחד אומר בשלשה ואחד אומר בחמשה עדותן בטלה. echad omer bishlosha
ve'echad omer bachamisha edutan betela. Is there a connection between these two
points—that if I say second and David says third, that's okay; if
I say second and David says fourth, that's not anymore okay? Are
we learning something from each other?
ואמאי? ve'amai? נימא שזה יודע בשני עיבורים וזה אינו יודע בשני עיבורים.
nima shezeh yode'a bishnei iburim vezeh eino yode'a bishnei iburim. Is that
like possible? Is that what we're talking about? One knows about the
new moon and one
doesn't? אלא לאו משום דרובה ידעת? ella lav mishum derubah yadat? Also
option—it's possible that somebody doesn't know most of the month. לעולם אימא
לך ברובה נמי לא ידעת. le'olam eima lach beruba nami lo yadat.
It is quite possible, גמרא gemara agrees with our discussion yesterday after
שיעור, shiur, it's very possible that somebody can not know which day
it is the whole month. ובשיפורא ידעת. ubeshipura yadat. בחד שיפורא אמר
דטעי. bechone shipura amar detei. בתרי שיפורא לא אמר דטעי. betrei shipura
lo amar detei. Now the שיפורא shipura is referring to the שופר
shofar of the new moon. Assuming that if there was one שופר
shofar blast for the new moon, then it's easy to make a
mistake because maybe you didn't hear it, maybe you're out of town,
maybe something something. But two blasts, like if there were two days
of ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh and you missed two blasts, less reasonable.
Now there's a whole long תוספות Tosafot about this issue. It's all
in Aramaic, and since we started a little late, I'm not sure
we're going to go there. So I just want to summarize it
very briefly. תוספות Tosafot is saying we're doing everything we can to
exonerate somebody on the tiniest things. And now you're going to say
it's the third, I'm going to say it's the fourth, and we're
going to be like, yeah, it's fine, let's just hang him. Let's
just not. make sense. So what he points to us is that
the issue is if we say yes, it was Monday. I think
Monday was the... what is it now? 28th? There you go. And
you think Monday was the 27th, but we're both sure it happened
during the traffic Monday to the city and we have... 27? The
27th today, give him money. And so Monday's going to be the
28th, yeah. Okay, but like we're talking about the same day of
the week, we're just not sure what the date of it was.
Then that עדות edut the testimony will be accepted, but we are
not sure which day it was and which date it was, then
it's not not accepted, too much too much uncertainty. All right.
We're moving from this discussion since we're anyway discussing again the עיבור
ibur and the position of the days of the the days of
the month vis-a-vis the beginning of the month. We're going to talk
a little bit about ברכת לבנה, Birkat HaLevana, which also was a
discussion yesterday after הבדלה. Havdalah. When do we say ברכת לבנה? Birkat
HaLevana? This is all happens to be current. Okay. Last night. Last
night, yeah. אמר רב אחא בר חנינא אמר רב אסי אמר רבי
יוחנן עד כמה מברכין על החודש. Amar Rav Acha bar Chanina amar
Rav Assi amar Rabbi Yochanan ad kama mevar'chin al ha-chodesh. How how
many days from ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh do we have for saying
ברכת לבנה? Birkat HaLevana? רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan answers, עד שתתמלא פגימתה.
ad she-titmale pegimata.
So that's... we'll leave this for later. Okay,
so we have the moon and this is considered the פגימה. pegima.
This is considered the part that is פגום, pagum, that is missing.
Okay. So how much is the מילוי miluy of this missing? Right?
This is ראש חודש. Rosh Chodesh. How much is the מילוי miluy
of this? Is it this or is it this? Okay? That's going
to be the discussion. How far can we talk?
וכמה? Ve-kama? אמר רב יעקב בר אידי אמר רב יהודה עד שבעה.
Amar Rav Yaakov bar Iddi amar Rav Yehuda ad shiva.
רב יהודה's Rav Yehuda opinion is seven. ונהרדעי, Ve-naharda'ei, which is our
system also, אמרי עד ששה עשר, amri ad shisha asar, until basically
the middle of the month we can still do it. ותרווייהו כרבי
יוחנן סבירא להו. Ve-travaihu ke-Rabbi Yochanan sevira le-hu. Both of them fulfill
what רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said, that this empty space needs to
be filled.
להויה כי יתרא ולהויה כי נפיא. Le-havei ke-yitra ve-le-havei ke-nafya. One says
יתר, yeter, which is like the string of the bow. So one
says it should look like a bow and the other one says
it should look like a sieve, it should be a full round
thing. So both opinions valid, lots of discussions, and Kabbalistic
discussions about the moon and the meaning of ברכת לבנה. Birkat HaLevana.
אמר ליה
רב אחא מדפתי לרבינא. Amar lei Rav Acha mi-Difti le-Ravina. Now we
have a conversation between רב אחא Rav Acha and רבינא. Ravina. ולברך
הטוב והמטיב. U-levarech HaTov VeHaMeitiv. So okay, got it. מחדש חודשים, Mechadesh
Chodashim, the blessing of the לבנה levana of the new moon, we
can say for maybe only seven days. Can we say also, or
maybe only, הטוב והמטיב, HaTov VeHaMeitiv, another blessing for the continuation of
those days? Or where is the place for that blessing in our
blessing of the new moon? אמר ליה אטו כי חסר מברכינן דיין
האמת דלברך הטוב והמטיב? Amar lei atu ki chasar mevar'chinan Dayan HaEmet
de-levarech HaTov VeHaMeitiv? רגע. Rega. You want to put a special blessing
for us adding days to the moon, but we don't say, are
we also going to say a blessing for subtracting, like דיין האמת,
Dayan HaEmet, which we say when somebody dies? Right? הטוב והמטיב HaTov
VeHaMeitiv we say on good news. דיין האמת Dayan HaEmet we say
on bad news. So if we consider this טוב, tov,
this should be דיין האמת, Dayan HaEmet, right, the continuation of the
moon... Charlie has a pretty picture for later.
And the answer is לברכינהו לתרווייהו. Levarechin'hu le-travaihu. Sure, say the blessing
for both. But the גמרא Gemara ends, כיוון דהיינו אורחיה לא מברכינן.
keivan de-hainu orchei lo mevar'chinan. And we can look quickly at רש''י.
Rashi. בכל חודש בריאת עולם כמנהגו היא ואין
כאן דין פורענות בחסרונה ולא הטבתה לנו חסד במילואה. Bechol chodesh beri'at
olam ke-minhago hi ve-ein kan din puranut be-chesrona ve-lo hatavata lanu chesed
be-milu'ah. But what is רש''י Rashi saying? There's a difference between us
recognizing השם's Hashem creation and between us thanking השם Hashem for something
good that happened to us. When we look at the moon, we're
acknowledging השם's Hashem creation and we're basically, it's a kind of a
wow, this is something that happens. This is not something that's personally
good for me. הטוב והמטיב HaTov VeHaMeitiv has other opportunities that we
say it, like if we already said בורא פרי הגפן Borei Pri
HaGafen and now somebody's bringing a second bottle of wine and we
want to say a special blessing for that. Somebody did kindness for
me, they brought me a second
bottle. So that's something that is ממש mamash like good for us.
But the ברכה bracha for the לבנה levana for the moon is
nothing that is got nothing to do with us. It's us being
outsiders kind of looking at the wow amazing creation that God gave.
Isn't there an association between the renewal of the Jewish people? Coming
up, coming up!
ואמר רב
אחא בר חנינא אמר רב אסי אמר רבי יוחנן Ve'amar Rav Acha
bar Chanina amar Rav Assi amar Rabbi Yochanan כל המברך על החודש
בזמנו כאילו מקבל פני שכינה. kol hamevarech al hachodesh bizmano ke'ilu mekabel
pnei Shechinah.
The statement of our רבנן rabbanan here is, if you say a
blessing of the new month in its time, it's as if you're
receiving the face of the שכינה, Shechinah, which also deserves like lengthy
conversation. What does it mean? What's so powerful? Is it, you know,
this is on a level of brainstorming,
is it because this is the first מצוה mitzvah we got as
a Jewish people, or is it such an important מצוה mitzvah and
that's why we got it as a first מצוה mitzvah of our
people where we actually have, I don't know if control, but like
at least a dialogue with time where we are present? I can
think of many hours a day when we're not present, and here
we're asked to ממש mamash be present. So I don't have all
the answers, but at least we can see the statement that this
is like accepting the שכינה. Shechinah. And why? We have a proof
text. In the matter of החודש הזה, hachodesh hazeh, this is the
new month, it says הזה. hazeh. And in another place it says
זה אלי ואנוהו. zeh Eli ve'anvehu. Where is that other place that
it says זה אלי ואנוהו? zeh Eli ve'anvehu? שירת הים. Shirat HaYam.
And what do we know about שירת הים? Shirat HaYam? That we
are told that ראתה שפחה מה שלא ראה יחזקאל בן בוזי. ra'ata
shifcha mah shelo ra'ah Yechezkel ben Buzi. Even the maidservant saw what
Ezekiel himself did not see, and we know that Ezekiel had amazing
visions. So what was the greatness that she saw? Everybody could see
the שכינה. Shechinah. The שכינה Shechinah was open to everybody.
Okay. תנא דבי רבי ישמעאל אלמלא זכו ישראל אלא להקביל פני אביהם
שבשמים כל חודש וחודש דיים. Tana d'vei Rabbi Yishmael ilmalei zachu Yisrael
ela lehakebil pnei avihem shebashamayim kol chodesh vechodesh dayam. If we did
nothing, only merited to welcome ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh every month and
look at his language, להקביל פני אביהן. lehakebil pnei avihen. It's like
to welcome our fatherly, our heavenly Father, right? If we saw that
every month, enough. For that, good enough that we were created, we
did our duty. אמר אביי הלכך נמרינהו מעומד. Amar Abaye hilkach nimrinhu
me'umad. That's why because it's so important and because it's a testimony
to the שכינה, Shechinah, that's why we say it standing up and
not sitting down. מרימר ומר זוטרא מכתפי ומברכי. Merimar u'Mar Zutra michatfei
u'mevarchi. Merimar and Mar Zutra were older and they would lean on,
some say on each other, but some say on their servants. So
regardless, they would be supported just in order to say this important
blessing. While standing, presumably. While standing, yeah, in order to be standing,
they were supported in order to be standing. So this is the
text we have in our... it's coming up, yes, ברכת הלבנה. Birkat
HaLevana. This is the actual... this is amazing, right? This is where
the source comes from. אמר ליה רב אחא לרב אשי
במערבא מברכי ברוך מחדש חודשים. Amar lei Rav Acha l'Rav Ashi b'ma'arava
mevarchi Baruch mechadesh chodashim. In the west, which we know is not
here, in Israel,
they say the blessing ברוך מחדש חודשים. Baruch mechadesh chodashim. That's the
blessing we say! But that is, okay, רגע, rega, that's the last
line. Exactly. That is our חתימה, chatima, our signature. And we see
there's a little bit of discussion that they hint but they don't
actually go into. And again, in another life it would be fascinating
to go into. אמר ליה הני נשי דידן נמי מברכי. Amar lei
hani neshei didan nami mevarchi. So there is a discussion that's not
happening about women's place vis-a-vis ברכת הלבנה. Birkat HaLevana. Yes. Ah, so
this is something I don't understand. I've been coming to this שול
shul for twelve years. Yes. And we are supposedly the שול shul
that's really supportive of women. I don't think I've ever seen a
woman say ברכת הלבנה. Birkat HaLevana. Women don't...
רגע. rega. Okay, so it's really unusual. We certainly didn't have it
last night. I don't want to make your חס וחלילה chas v'chalila
anything שלא במקומו, shelo bimkomo,
but exactly because what they're saying, if it's such a short blessing,
ברכת הלבנה Birkat HaLevana should fall under the category of מצות עשה
שהזמן גרמה, mitzvat asei shehazman grama, right? A positive מצות עשה שהזמן
גרמה, mitzvat asei shehazman grama, positive time-bound commandment. Women are exempt from
most, but some of them they are...
So we have חנוכה Hanukkah candles, we have a few other examples
that נשים חייבות. nashim chayevot.
There's a whole more complicated discussion, not now, but there's a whole
discussion in the back of this of women, the moon, the third,
fourth day of the month when we can start saying קידוש לבנה
Kiddush Levana and women's, when can women get married?
Way like beyond what I can do justice to right now. But
what we see also what the rabbis are doing, it's as if
somebody here did exactly what's happened in our שיעור shiur right now
and said, we're not talking about this because the topic like disappears.
Right? They say women should say the blessing too, but the custom
is for women not to say קידוש לבנה. Kiddush Levana. Whether we
want to break some mold, we should probably study what's behind the
scene here before we go on the barricades for קידוש לבנה. Kiddush
Levana. But it is a rather extended time period. It's not like,
you know, it's like you have two weeks to do it in
our context. Almost, yes, almost two weeks. So it's not like a
woman is being imposed upon it in terms of a rather... So
that's exactly the question. So, but they say in that case, if
you're saying that, then women should be doing.
Subtext meaning, as we know, women don't do. Why don't women do
קידוש לבנה? Kiddush Levana? Because
there's also a lot of men who don't do it.
Well, yeah, and that's another, I don't ever remember getting a מנין
minyan for it. As Rabbi Linder would say, well moving on. Okay,
can you just briefly explain that about when, when the women would
get married and this idea of the days of the moon? I
don't think I can do it briefly, but there
is something that says that a woman gets married on the fourth
day. What is that fourth day? How is that related to קידוש
לבנה Kiddush Levana and the moon? So there's a whole like why
Wednesday and how is that related to שבת Shabbat and then what
is the meaning of the fourth day, and the fourth day is
also the day that the מאורות me'orot were created, right? The sun
and the moon were created. And that's the day that the moon
was shrunk, shrunken. Like you know, the sun and the moon were
supposedly the same size, but that's the day the moon was shrunk.
Why was it shrunk? What do the women have to do with
the moon?
I can't answer all of it, but it's all somehow connected and
the custom has become for women not to say it. We are
moving on. And to be married on the fourth day? Yeah, and
unlike a lot of people get married on Wednesday, on Wednesday.
Well, okay. Or Tuesday. אלא, Ela, כי דרב יהודה דאמר רב יהודה.
kideRav Yehuda de'amar Rav Yehuda. Basically they do the same thing that
happened to us now, they're saying, forget it, we're not talking about
it, let's talk about the ברכה beracha itself. And now we have
the text that is our text basically. ברוך וכולי, Baruch vechulei, right,
etc, השם, Hashem, אשר במאמרו ברא שחקים, asher bama'amaro bara shechakim, in
his saying, in his אמירה, amira, in his statement, he created heaven,
וברוח פיו כל צבאם, uveruach piv kol tzeva'am, and the breath of
his mouth, his whole heavenly forces. חוק וזמן נתן להם שלא ישנו
את תפקידם. Chok vezman natan lahem shelo yeshanu et tafkidam. He gave
them law and timely, timelessness, that they will not change their role.
ששים ושמחים לעשות רצון קונם. Sasim vesamechim la'asot retzon konam. They are
joyfully hastening to do the will of their creator. פועלי אמת
שפעולתם אמת. Po'alei emet shepe'ulatam emet.
They are the truthful workers, if you will, that are doing truthful
acts. וללבנה אמר, Velalevana amar, and to the moon it said, שתתחדש
עטרת תפארת לעמוסי בטן. shetitchadesh ateret tiferet le'amusei vaten. It said to
the, he said to the moon, may you be renewed like the
crown of those that are loaded with good things. שהן עתידים להתחדש
כמותה, Shehen atidim lehitkhadesh kemotah, that they are going to be renewed
like her, which is the reference to the people of Israel what
you said before. ולפאר ליוצרם על שם כבוד מלכותו, Ulefa'er leyotzram al
shem kevod malchuto, and to glorify their creator for the name of
his kingdom, kingship. ברוך אתה השם מחדש חודשים. Baruch atah Hashem mechadesh
chodashim. Blessed are you who renews the month. And I think it's
moving to see the ברכה beracha in its, you know, words, the
way we do it right now. Totally, yeah. We mentioned that women's
connection with the cycle of the moon and their own cycle. I
mean that whole thing is so deep. Let me say just yes,
yes, yes.
Like there's a lot of stuff behind there that I can't, okay.
במי
אתה מוצא מלחמתה של תורה. Bemi atah motzei milchamtah shel Torah. Who
do you find somebody who fights for the Torah? במי שיש בידו
חבילות של משנה. Bemi sheyesh beyado chavilot shel Mishnah. And I'm not
sure if that answers the previous issue that we could not get
into, but the idea is that... Someone who can fight for the
תורה Torah is someone who has packs of משנה. Mishnah. Why packs
of משנה Mishnah and not packs of תורה? Torah? Right, previously we
said that in order to fight an אפיקורוס Apikorus you need a
lot of תורה. Torah. But this is slightly different. This is how
to fight for the תורה. Torah. So what what is the issue
with the משנה? Mishnah? As we know, the תורה Torah has a
lot of contradictions, or hopefully we'll see in the next page repetitions.
The משנה Mishnah is the tool that helps us reconcile what happens
in the תורה Torah in different places. And therefore in order to
fight for the תורה Torah you need to know משנה. Mishnah. כרב
יוסף אנפשיה. K'Rav Yosef anafshei. He said that about himself. ורב תבואות
בכח שור. V'rav t'vuot b'choach shor. תבואה T'vuah
the grain means תורה Torah as a reference for תורה Torah and
שור shor an ox is a reference for יוסף Yosef because that
was the symbol of the tribe or of יוסף. Yosef. So רב
יוסף Rav Yosef says about himself yes I am strong in תורה
Torah like יוסף. Yosef. If there's any more meaning underneath, I will
not go into it. So emphasis on the all on? Yes, on
the משנה, Mishnah, תורה Torah on the. All right, picking up back
from the משנה Mishnah of this chapter. אחד אומר בשתי שעות. Echad
omer b'shtei sha'ot. Now we're looking at hourly discrepancy. This conversation we
just finished was about days on the month. Now we're looking at
hours. אמר רב שימי בר אשי: Amar Rav Shimi bar Ashi: לא
שנו אלא שעות. Lo shanu ela sha'ot. Like if it's just a
couple of hours discrepancy we accept it, but it depends where those
couple of hours are as we'll see. Okay, so the difference between
10 and 11 in the morning or between 2 and 3 is
not the same as the difference between 4 AM and 5 AM
or 4:30 AM and 5:30 AM. Because אבל אחד אומר קודם הנץ
החמה ואחד אומר לאחר הנץ החמה עדותן בטילה. Aval echad omer kodem
ha-neitz ha-chamah v'echad omer l'achar ha-neitz ha-chamah edutan beteilah.
If one says before sunrise and one says after sunrise even though
the objective time was little, the testimony is cancelled. פשיטא Peshita says
the גמרא. Gemara. אלא אחד אומר קודם הנץ החמה ואחד אומר בתוך
הנץ החמה. Ela echad omer kodem ha-neitz ha-chamah v'echad omer b'toch ha-neitz
ha-chamah. הא נמי פשיטא. Ha nami peshita.
What if one says it was right before sunrise and one says
no it was exactly during sunrise? We also disqualify it. Why? מהו
דתימא הך בגלויא קאי וזהרורי בעלמא הוא דחזא קא משמע לן. Mahu
deteima hach begiluya ka'i v'zahrurei be'alma hu dechaza ka mashma lan. All
right,
so now the גמרא Gemara suggests that besides the discrepancy in time
which is minor, right, the second between whatever
we don't know whenever sunrise is now, let's say 6:15 and 6:30,
that's like nothing in matters of time of the testimony, it's nothing.
But what they suggest, wait, but what they suggest is that in
order to see the sunrise when somebody else doesn't see the sunrise
you have had to have been in a different location and therefore
it disqualifies the testimony not because your hours, your hours could have
been very close, closer than what the משנה Mishnah says, but your
location must have been different. You maybe were on a taller place
or whatever, yes. Maybe it was a cloudy day.
Like the eclipse, right.
I've heard lengthy stories about that cloudy eclipse. Okay. All right. Back
in the משנה Mishnah we have a lengthy discussion about אותו היום
oto hayom on that day when they bring in the testimony that
no, the witness, sorry, to hear the testimony he,
אותו היום oto hayom on that very day. The גמרא Gemara asks
אותו היום ותו לא? oto hayom v'tu lo? That day and that's
it? You want to flip back on מ mem in the middle.
Okay. So חנינא כזה Chanina k'zeh or חנינא תבי? Chanina Tavi? יש
לי ללמד זכות מעלים אותו ומושיבים אותו ביניהם ולא היה יורד משם
כל היום כולו אם יש ממש בדבריו שומעים לו. Yeish li lelamed
zechut ma'alim oto umoshivin oto beineihem v'lo hayah yored misham kol hayom
kulo im yeish mamash bidvarav shom'im lo. We call the witness and
he's not going down the whole day. If he has something serious,
something important to say, we don't let him go. What if he
doesn't? Okay, so they ask אותו היום ותו לא? oto hayom v'tu
lo? Like the whole day has to be there and no more,
not less, no more? והתניא V'hatanya we're taught אם יש ממש בדבריו
לא היה יורד משם לעולם. im yeish mamash bidvarav lo hayah yored
misham l'olam. If he has something important for our testimony, he's not
going down. He's not the witness. This is one of the disciples
who
moved up to the the תלמידים talmidim that is, yeah, ללמד זכות
lelamed zechut to the court. So he's not a witness for the,
he's like a, what do you call it, character witness? Right. He's
not one of the witnesses who saw the event but he's talking
about
the defendant.
Yes. Talking about the. אחד מן התלמידים echad min hatalmidim יש לי
ללמד עליו חובה yesh li lilamed alav chovah משתקים אותו mishtakim oso
but if he has זכות ללמד zchus lilamed מעלין אותו ומושיבין אותו
ma'alin oso umoshivin oso ולא היה יורד משם כל היום כולו. velo
haya yored misham kol hayom kulo.
Right. Okay.
Yes.
He's not a witness to the event but he wants to say
something good about the person. Okay.
All right. ואם אין ממש בדבריו ve'im ein mamash bidvarav אין יורד
כל היום כולו. ein yored kol hayom kulo. Like sorry that question
ואם אין ממש בדבריו ve'im ein mamash bidvarav if he says like
oh I don't know whatever Joe
Schmoe bakes cookies, not relevant. Okay. אין יורד כל היום כולו כדי
שלא תהא עליתו ירידה לו. ein yored kol hayom kulo kedei shelo
tehei aliyaso yeridah lo. It would be embarrassing for him to be
called up and then be sent away. So אביי Abaye says the
reconciliation of these two things is ואם אין ממש בדבריו. ve'im ein
mamash bidvarav. Like we have to really check if he's saying things
that matter to our case or don't matter to our case. Have
some substance
or no substance. Okay. מצאו
לו זכות matzu lo zchus if they find a merit
and then in the משנה mishnah there is a discussion that there
was they would not drink wine all day. יין yayin מאי טעמא
mai ta'ama why why are we mentioning
wine which I'm not sure why they have a lengthy discussion about
it but they do. Maybe we had a discussion about this actually
some other time here that there was no water. Water is not
as drinkable
so they had other drinks, maybe wine. Okay so why not wine?
אמר
רבי אחא בר חנינא אמר קרא amar Rabbi Acha bar Chanina amar
kra he quotes a פסוק pasuk I think from משלי Mishlei ולרוזנים
אי שכר velaroznim ei shachar שכר shachar העוסקים ברזו של עולם ha'oskim
berazo shel olam ואל ישתכרו. ve'al yishtakeru. רוזנים roznim can be translated
as like dukes, leaders, but also Hebrew root for רז. raz. רז
raz means secret. We studied this together that נכנס יין יצא סוד
nichnas yayin yatza sod right when wine enters secrets come out. If
they are dealing with the secrets of the world it's better that
they don't do it when they drink. Okay. Another, another
question about this. לא ראו lo ra'u
back. מאי mai what does it mean? What now what if they
don't find מצאו לו זכות? matzu lo zchus? Now they can't, they
have a hung jury right they have a hung court. אמר רב
פפא amar Rav Pappa פוטרים
אותו potrim oso dismiss
the guy there one second. The defendant. Dismiss. וכן אמר רבי יוחנן
vechen amar Rabbi Yochanan פוטרים אותו. potrim oso. אמר ליה רב פפא
לאביי amar lei Rav Pappa le'Abaye ופטרא מעיקרא uftara mei'ikara
like
should we just dismiss him immediately? Why? Because in the משנה mishnah
it talks about what if we have a hung court of
35-36? No movement, he can be dismissed. But if we have a
court that is
12-11 to the 23, so we don't have enough like we need
at least two more in order to find him guilty. So do
we dismiss him or do we add people?
Okay so should we just dismiss him? אמר ליה amar lei הכי
אמר רבי יוחנן hachi amar Rabbi Yochanan כדי שלא יצאו מבית דין
מעורבבין. kedei shelo yetzu mibeis din me'urvavin.
It's not good for the בית דין beis din to go out
mixed up. The בית דין beis din should come out when they
have a decision. If they don't have a decision they have to
give up the case. איכא דאמרי ika de'amri some say אמר ליה
רב פפא לאביי amar lei Rav Pappa le'Abaye ולמה לי יוסיפו velama
li yosifu
but wait in the משנה mishnah it says add people, right you
know you can add from 23 until 71 just so that you
have a judgment. מבית דין קמא mibeis din kama you could have,
which way is it basically? Do you add or do you dismiss
the guy? אמר ליה רב יוסף amar lei Rav Yosef תאא כוותך
tei kavatach like
yes it's done both ways. It can be done both ways. You
can add or you can dismiss the guy. דתניא detanya רבי יוסי
אומר Rabbi Yosi omer כשם שאין מוסיפין על בית דין של שבעים
ואחד כך אין מוסיפין על בית דין של עשרים ושלושה. keshem she'ein
mosifin al beis din shel shivim ve'echad kach ein mosifin al beis
din shel esrim ushlosha. So just like the בית דין beis din
of 71 we don't add anymore. If it's hung, it's done. If
it's 35-36 they're going
and the guy's let go. So some say רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi
says also בית דין beis din of 23 we don't add until
71. This is going to extend the deliberations too much. We let
him go. But if you have extra people, go. All right.
תנו רבנן tanu rabanan says... In דיני ממונות dinei mamonot in civil
cases you can say the judgment has grown old, tedious, hard, difficult,
and in דיני נפשות dinei nefashot don't say that. מאי נזדקן הדין?
mai nizdaken hadin? What does it mean? We just explained it. What
does it mean נזדקן הדין? nizdaken hadin? אילימא קש דינא? ilima kash
dina? קש, kash, קשה, kasheh, it became hard. Wait, you mean דיני
ממונות dinei mamonot you say it and דיני נפשות dinei nefashot you
don't say it? איפכא מיבעי ליה! ipcha mibei lei! It should be
the opposite. דיני נפשות dinei nefashot should be the hard one and
not דיני ממונות. dinei mamonot. אמר רב הונא בר מנוח משמיה דרבכא
בריה דרב, amar Rav Huna bar Manoach mishmeih de-Ravecha breih de-Rav, איכא
דאמרי ika de-amrei yes, also it can be the opposite. רב אשי
Rav Ashi objects. He says, אמר לעולם לא תיפוך. amar le-olam lo
tipoch. No. ומאי נזדקן הדין? u-mai nizdaken hadin? חכם דינא. chacham dina.
Okay, so sometimes when the judgment is like aged, it became more
wise, it became more understood.
Okay. מתיבי, meitivei, a challenge. גדול שבדינים gadol she-ba-dayanim who would say
this? Who would say this about the judgment, that the judgment has
become difficult or that the judgment has become challenging? גדול שבדינים, gadol
she-ba-dayanim, the great one among the judges say this? אי אמרת בשלמא
חכם דינא, היינו דאמר גדול. אלא אי אמרת קש דינא, לא סגי
דלא אמר גדול? כיסופי הוא דקמיכסף נפשיה. ei amrat bishlama chacham dina,
hainu de-amar gadol. Ela ei amrat kash dina, lo sagi de-lo amar
gadol? kisuffei hu de-kamichsaf nafsheih. Question: If the great דיין dayan
of the בית דין Beis Din says, ooh, this is really difficult,
is that like appropriate for him to say that?
It's one thing to say it,
let's say it's one thing to say it when the judgment is
wise and he says, oh yes, this judgment has aged, it's good.
But what if it's not? What if they didn't reach a conclusion
and it's like some difficulty? Do we still want the גדול gadol
to say it? Is it not embarrassing? But the גמרא Gemara says
אין. in. אינו דומה מתבייש מעצמו למתבייש מאחרים. eino domeh mitbayesh me-atsmo
le-mitbayesh me-acherim. It is not the same to be embarrassed between one
and a person and themselves to being embarrassed from others.
Wait, but the opposite can also be true. Like he might say,
oh this דין din is very wise, so now he's not embarrassed,
he's showing off, right?
איכא דאמרי, ika de-amrei, אי אמרת בשלמא קש דינא, היינו דאינו דומה
מתבייש מעצמו למתבייש מאחרים. ei amrat bishlama kash dina, hainu de-eino domeh
mitbayesh me-atsmo le-mitbayesh me-acherim. Okay, I get it. The one who is
embarrassed from himself is not the same like embarrassed from others. אלא
אי אמרת חכם דינא, ela ei amrat chacham dina, but what if
the judgment is wise? Now he's showing off. גדול השבוחי משבח נפשיה?
gadol hashbuchei meshabeach nafsheih? Is it okay for the big דיין dayan
to like,
how would you say, exalt himself or like say good things about
himself? And we have a פסוק pasuk that says, יהללך זר ולא
פיך. yehalelcha zar ve-lo picha. You should be lauded by another, by
a stranger, and not by your own mouth. Don't tell your own
שבחות, shvachot, your own praises. It's funny, in Israel, modern Hebrew,
you make fun of this פסוק, pasuk, יהללך זר ולא פיך. yehalelcha
zar ve-lo picha. You should have a stranger praise you and not
you yourself. But if you change the vowel on the ו, vav,
ולו פיך, velo picha, but you say יהללך זר ואלו פיך yehalelcha
zar ve-ilo picha it means a stranger should praise you, and if
there's no stranger,
your mouth should praise you! Psychology's really interesting. All American psychology.
Okay. שאני מילתא דבי דינא. shani milta de-bei dina. This is, okay,
the גמרא Gemara says wait, this is different when it comes to
the דין. din. When it comes to the דין, din, the גדול
gadol has a job that's beyond whether that praises himself or whether
that doesn't praise himself. He's like a channel in a way. This
goes through him and is not about him. דגדול רמיא, de-gadol ramya,
כדתנן, ke-datnan, גמרו את הדבר היו מכניסים אותם. gamru et hadavar hayu
machnisim otam. When they decided what's the verdict, they bring them in
and they pronounce the judgment. גדול שבדינים אומר. gadol she-ba-dayanim omer. The
greatest among the judges says, איש פלוני אתה זכאי, איש פלוני אתה
חייב. ish ploni ata zakai, ish ploni ata chayav. The גדול gadol
says whether it looked good or looked bad, whether it's a compliment
to himself or not a compliment to himself, he has to pronounce
the judgment whether a person is זכאי zakai or a person is
חייב. chayav. הדרן עלך היו בודקים, hadran alach hayu bodkim, we are
going to the top of מב. Mem-Bet.
Deep breath.
All right. So now that we have a verdict with our poor
guy, and if he's let go, goodbye, he's free to go. But
what if he's guilty? We will now have to deal with how
we punish him. נגמר הדין, nigmar hadin, משנה mishnah at the top
of
מב, Mem-Bet, פרק שישי, perek shishi, סנהדרין, Sanhedrin, נגמר הדין. nigmar hadin.
נגמר הדין, nigmar hadin,
judgment... היה חוץ לבית לבית דין. Haya chutz l'veit l'veit din. The
house of stoning, there was a special place where people would be
stoned, and that was outside the בית דין, Beit Din, שנאמר, she'ne'emar,
הוצא את המקלל. Hotze et hamikallel. Okay. The פסוק pasuk that is
key, you'll see in a minute behind me, the פסוק pasuk which
is key to our understanding where is the סקילה, sekilah, where is
the stoning, is from Leviticus, the end of פרשת אמור. Parshat Emor.
We have a situation of a person who is cursing another. We
are instructed to take him out, אל מחוץ למחנה. el michutz l'machaneh.
You can see the full פסוק pasuk probably most everybody has it
on the side. הוצא את המקלל אל מחוץ למחנה וסמכו כל השומעים
את ידיהם ורגמו אותו כל
העדה. Hotze et hamikallel el michutz l'machaneh v'samchu kol hashomim et yadeihem
v'ragmu oto kol ha'edah. He's stoned outside of the camp. A number
of those words there are going to be important. Okay.
Take out the one who's cursing.
אחד Echad now what's the procedure? אחד
עומד על פתח בית דין והסודרין בידו. Echad omed al petach beit
din v'hasudarin b'yado. So now the judgment is over,
we're taking our poor guy to be stoned, and there is, you
can see in רש"י, Rashi, חוץ לבית הדין רחוק מבית הדין קצת.
chutz l'veit hadin rachok m'beit hadin kzat. Unclear what was the distance.
You know, was it from, whatever, from here to Starbucks? Is it
from here to just across the street? How far is that distance?
Yes, but you'd have to get him far out of camp because
otherwise there'd be the potential for coming in contact with the guy's
corpse once he's dead. And you think that because it makes sense
we're just going to skip a whole עמוד amud talking about that?
You just, you're not going to let me go through my beautiful
chart and everything? No, no, no. Yes, בסדר. beseder. Listen to the
order here. Okay. This is the procedure. אחד עומד על פתח בית
דין. Echad omed al petach beit din. So after the guy's being
taken out, again, distance discussed רש"י Rashi and רמב"ם, Rambam, some say
further, some closer, one person is still left behind in the בית
דין Beit Din with a scarf or a something in his hand,
a cloth, bright cloth in his hand. וסוס רחוק ממנו כדי שיהיה
רואהו. Vsus rachok mimeno kedei she'ye'hei ro'ehu. אומר אחד יש לי ללמד
עליו זכות. Omer echad yesh li lilamed alav zechut. So now picture,
we're taking the guy to be executed, somebody's staying at the entrance
of the בית דין Beit Din and all of a sudden somebody
runs and says, "Blah blah blah, I have something good to say
about him, wait!" הלה מניף בסודרין. Hala menif basudarin. The person at
the entrance of the בית דין Beit Din can wave his scarf
and stop the procedure. והסוס רץ ומעמידן. V'hasus ratz u'ma'amidan. The horse
runs, the horse
runs and they stop everything. ואפילו הוא אומר יש לי ללמד על
עצמי זכות. V'afilu hu omer yesh li lilamed al atzmi zechut. Even
if the condemned person now said, "Oh,
I have something good to say about myself, I forgot to mention
earlier," מחזירין אותו אפילו ארבע וחמש פעמים ובלבד שיש ממש בדבריו. Machzirin
oto afilu arba v'chamesh pe'amim u'vilvad she'yesh mamash bidvarav. We need there
to be some substance to what he's saying, but we will bring
him back as many times as possible so that if possible we
can exonerate him. And now it's important to note that he's not
going quietly.
Okay? The defendant that is now guilty, it's not like they're taking
him quietly, but there is a כרוז, karoz, there is an announcer
that goes with him and he says, "Joe Schmo, son of Shmo-Joe,
whatever, on this day at this hour at this place, this is
what happened, anyone knows anything?" So it's a loud procedure that involves
everybody, which kind of speaks to the power of community in these
situations and to the desire, I think, not to come to this
moment where they take someone's life. And we know, we'll see it
in a minute, I just... Was this only in the instance of
the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, the Great סנהדרין, Sanhedrin, that this takes
place? Excellent question. Well coming up, what's the procedure of the בית
דין? Beis Din? Like we already talked about where is it. Yeah,
we're going to, it's going to be still on הר הבית, Har
Habayit, you know. Okay, so those are all excellent questions which the
גמרא Gemara is asking too. In a minute it's going to ask,
when it says בית, beit, just let's see. You'll see. A lot
will be answered in 10 minutes hopefully.
I'm just going to move on.
Okay. ובית הסקילה חוץ לבית הדין הוה ותו לא? U'veit hasekila chutz
l'veit hadin hava v'tu lo? בית הסקילה, Beit hasekila, do you mean
it was outside the court and that's it and nothing more?
והתניא, V'hatanya, we're taught elsewhere, בית הסקילה היה חוץ לשלוש מחנות. Beit
hasekila haya chutz l'shalosh machanot. בית הסקילה Beit hasekila should be outside
three camps. Alright, so let's do a quick chalkboard maneuver. Take the
moon away. Good with the moon. Alright, so we have... Let's say
בית המקדש *Beit Hamikdash*, right? And then another camp, we'll call it
מחנה Machaneh לויה *Machaneh Leviya*. And then מחנה machaneh. ישראל *Machaneh Yisrael*.
And if we think about the desert, the same, right? The משכן
*Mishkan* was inside, then the לוויים *Levi'im*, then Israel.
So when we say, this is our question for this whole עמוד
*amud*, when we say מחוץ לבית הדין *michutz lebeit hadin*, do we
mean בית הדין *beit hadin* is here and this is מחוץ *michutz*?
Do we mean בית הדין *beit hadin* is here and this is
מחוץ *michutz*? Or do we mean no matter where it is, it's
outside all three camps and here is the stoning site?
That's the question that's in front of us. Okay.
And we have a תניא *tanya* that says בית הסקילה Beis HaSekilah
היה *Beit haskila haya*, תניא *tanya* says דהתניא *dehatanya*, בית הסקילה Beis
HaSekilah היה חוץ לשלוש מחנות chutz l'shalosh machanot. *Bet haskila haya chutz
leshalosh machanot*. In yes, כדאמר *kede'amar*, כדאמר *kede'amar*, והא כדתני הכי נפקא
מינא מהא בשם *veha keditni hachi nafka mina meha bashem*. So we
can get to the bottom. Okay.
There is, why is it saying so that we will learn about
the outside of three camps and not just outside of one מחנה
*machaneh*? But the discussion is not over. The discussion, I'm just giving
you the heads up, you know where we're going, no suspense. The
discussion is going to compare and contrast two פסוקים *psukim* that mention
this word, מחוץ למחנה mi-chutz l'machaneh. *michutz lamachaneh*, and we're going to
see which one from them,
which one from them does it make more sense to learn from?
This פסוק pasuk *pasuk* or that פסוק *pasuk*? And when we decide,
we will know if it means outside one camp or outside three
camps. Because there is also a possibility that בית דין beis din
*beit din* is outside the camp anyway.
So what do we do then? Where do we go? Like, is
it then okay just to do it outside the front door or
do we still have to go out? So all this is trying
to be discussed right now.
Let's see if we, okay, if we can make it. דאי נפיק
בית דינא ויתיב חוץ לשלוש מחנות הדינן בית הסקילה Beis HaSekilah חוץ
לבית דין *De'i nafik beit dina veyatib chutz leshalosh machanot hadinan beit
haskila chutz lebeit din*. Exactly what we mentioned right now. We have
a conflict in our understanding whether the words that are talked about,
where the מקלל Mekalel, *mekalel*, where's the one who's cursing, מחוץ למחנה
mi-chutz l'machaneh *michutz lamachaneh* mean immediately outside the camp or includes all
three camps? Okay.
The first reason why we want this to be far from the
בית דין *beit din* is כי היכי דלא מיתחזי בית דין רוצחין
*ki heichi dela mitchazi beit din rotzchin*. We do not want the
בית דין *beit din* to look like a murderous בית דין *beit
din* that on the, you know, front door people are being killed.
You can see רש״י *Rashi* in the middle of the column: כי
היכי דלא ליתחזי בית דין רוצחין דגנאי הדבר *ki heichi dela litchazi
beit din rotzchin degnai hadavar*. This is like a bad thing for
the בית דין *beit din*. דתנן *detnan* in מכות *Makkot*, סנהדרין ההורגת
פעם אחת בשבוע נקראת חבלנית *Sanhedrin hahoreget pa'am achat beshavua nikret chavlanit*,
וכל שכן אם יהיה קרוב למקומם מחזי מקום איבוד נפשות *vechol sheken
im yihye karov lemekomam mechazi mekom ibud nefashot*. The בית דין *beit
din* is going to start looking like an execution place instead of
a place of justice where people can come with their cases. So
we want to separate those two entities.
Another reason: אינמי כי היכי דתהוי ליה הצלה *Inami ki heichi detihavei
lei hatzala*.
Another reason why we want to separate the distance between a בית
דין *beit din* and the execution is because we want another chance
for הצלה *hatzala*, right, for saving our poor guy. And so the
longer the distance and the כרוז *karoz*, right, the proclamation, then the
better chance we have to save him. אמינא הני מילי *Amina hani
mili*, okay so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going to ask,
exactly what Charlie said, that makes sense that it shouldn't happen right
here. But makes sense is not enough for us. We need complicated
פסוקים *psukim* in order to
substantiate our claim. Okay. דתנו רבנן *detanu rabanan*, הוצא את המקלל אל
מחוץ למחנה hotzei es ha’Mekalel el m’chutz lamachaneh. *Hotze et hamekalel el
michutz lamachaneh*, חוץ לג׳ מחנות *chutz legimmel machanot*. My understanding is that
when you say, and we'll see later why, so we have to
understand that while we, or me, reading the דף *daf*, I don't
yet have all the information, but the rabbis of the תלמוד *Talmud*,
they have a lot of information in the back of their mind
that we are not yet privy to, so that they already know,
but they'll tell us later. Let's just plow through to it.
Okay. So it says, take the מקלל Mekalel *mekalel*, take the curser
from outside the camp, חוץ לג׳ מחנות *chutz legimmel machanot*, that's our
understanding. אתה אומר חוץ לג׳ מחנות או אינו אלא חוץ למחנה chutz
l'machaneh. אחת *Ata omer chutz legimmel machanot o eino ela chutz lemachaneh
achat*? Wait, I want to question this. Outside of three camps? or
outside of one camp? נאמר כאן מחוץ למחנה. mi-chutz l'machaneh. Okay, it
says in the matter of the מקלל, Mekalel, מחוץ למחנה. mi-chutz l'machaneh,
And now in another issue, which is פרים הנשרפים, Parim HaNisrafim, they're
bulls that are being brought up as sacrifices like for a כהן
Kohen that transgressed something that the punishment is כרת, karet, for example.
Also פרים הנשרפים, Parim HaNisrafim, it says חוץ למחנה. About the פרים
הנשרפים, Parim HaNisrafim, we know already that that's outside three camps. So
מה להלן חוץ לשלוש מחנות אף כאן חוץ לשלוש מחנות. Ma lehallan
chutz l'shalosh machanot af kan chutz l'shalosh machanot. It's like פרים הנשרפים
Parim HaNisrafim is outside three camps, the מקלל Mekalel also should be.
Not so simple.
התם מנלן, Hatam minalan, because how do we know about the פרים
parim that it's outside three camps? It also only says מחוץ למחנה
mi-chutz l'machaneh, in the singular. So how can we apply this here?
It should have said מחוץ למחנות. mi-chutz l'machanot. רגע. Rega. תנו רבנן:
Tanu rabanan: והוציא את כל הפר אל מחוץ למחנה, Ve-hotzi et kol
ha-par el mi-chutz l'machaneh, חוץ לשלוש מחנות. This is our teaching. Again
I'm asking you, אתה אומר חוץ לשלוש מחנות או אינו אלא חוץ
למחנה אחת? Atah omer chutz l'shalosh machanot o eino ela chutz l'machaneh
achat? רגע. Rega. Now what is, I'm asking you again, I'm not
clear. פרים הנשרפים Parim HaNisrafim says מחוץ למחנה. mi-chutz l'machaneh. מחנה is
in singular. How did you come up with three? Now they're going
to bring us three situations of sacrifices, sacrificial related rituals, don't like
the word rituals, but use it loosely. Procedures,
thank you, better, where in three cases it says מחוץ למחנה, mi-chutz
l'machaneh, therefore we understand from it that each one comes to increase
on the previous one and therefore we understand that it's three camps.
Okay,
so one of them is in פרים הנשרפים, Parim HaNisrafim, in these
bulls that are being burned, it says מחוץ למחנה, mi-chutz l'machaneh one.
Two, כשהוא אומר אל מחוץ למחנה בפר העדה, kshehu omer el mi-chutz
l'machaneh b'par ha-edah, now we have a bull that atones for the
community, שאין תלמוד לומר שהרי כבר נאמר שרף אותו כאשר שרף את
הפר
הראשון. she-ein talmud lomar she-harei kvar ne'emar saraf oto ka-asher saraf et
ha-par ha-rishon. About פר
העדה, par ha-edah, we have פרים הנשרפים, Parim HaNisrafim,
פר העדה, par ha-edah,
and in a minute we'll have the דשן, deshen, the like leftover
ashes of the sacrifices. About them also it says מחוץ למחנה. mi-chutz
l'machaneh So if I already know that פרים הנשרפים Parim HaNisrafim are
מחוץ למחנה, mi-chutz l'machaneh right, and I know that it says שרף
אותו כאשר שרף, saraf oto ka-asher saraf, right, you do to the
פר העדה par ha-edah like you did to the פרים הנשרפים. Parim
HaNisrafim. Why do I say they're מחוץ למחנה mi-chutz l'machaneh again? ליתן
לו מחנה שניה. Liten lo machaneh shniyah. Now I can get the
second camp. Okay, camp one, camp two. וכשהוא אומר אל מחוץ למחנה
בדשן u-kshe-hu omer el mi-chutz l'machaneh ba-deshen in the beginning of פרשת
צו Parshat Tzav when the Torah says on the priest, instructs the
priest when he starts his day, to take the דשן אל מחוץ
למחנה, deshen el mi-chutz l'machaneh, to take the leftover ashes outside the
camp, שאין תלמוד לומר שהרי כבר נאמר על שפך הדשן ישרף. she-ein
talmud lomar she-harei kvar ne'emar al shefech ha-deshen yisaref. We already know
the ashes are
מחוץ למחנה mi-chutz l'machaneh from the
previous ones. Why do we need it again? ליתן לו מחנה שלישית.
Liten lo מחנה shlishit. Great. You would think we would go home
happy, but no, we're in the Gemara, we are not going home
yet. All right, so מחוץ למחנה m’chutz lamachaneh, is a, the word
comes up, comes up with the מקלל, Mekalel comes up with פרים
הנשרפים. Parim HaNisrafim. We just showed that it will be outside of
three camps. But guess what? This word, these two words, come up
in something called שחוטי חוץ. shchutei chutz. שחוטי חוץ shchutei chutz is
somebody bringing up a sacrifice that should be קודש, kodesh, not in
the קודש, kodesh, outside the קודש. kodesh. That's why they're called שחוטי
חוץ. shchutei chutz. They're being slaughtered outside the appropriate place. Also there
the words מחוץ למחנה m’chutz lamachaneh. come up. So how about I
learn from them? Very possible that maybe and then it's only one
מחנה. So maybe this whole exercise here was for naught. רגע. Rega.
סו רגע, So rega, hold. ונילף משחוטי חוץ, V'neilaf mishchutei chutz, מה
להלן חוץ למחנה אחת אף כאן
חוץ למחנה אחת? ma lehallan chutz l'machaneh achat af kan chutz l'machaneh
achat? שחוטי חוץ, shchutei chutz, מחוץ למחנה m’chutz lamachaneh, means outside one
camp, let's also say that the מקלל Mekalel, is outside one. אדרבה.
Adarabbah. And you're right, let's consider this. משחוטי חוץ האי הוי ליה
למילף שכן אדם חוטא בנשמה פיגול. Mishchutei chutz hai havei leih l'meilaf
sheken adam chotei baneshamah pigul. You are right, I have four things
in common with both. to these statements. And now maybe this chart
makes a little more sense. Okay, the מקלל Mekalel and the פרים
Parim have four things in common. הוצא, Hotzei, take out, it says
about the מקלל, Mekalel, take him out, it says about the פרים,
Parim, take them out, and מחוץ למחנה, also about the פרים. Parim.
This is in order to make a מצווה mitzvah כשר, kosher, right?
The מקלל is because he needs to be punished, atoned through his
punishment. Also the פרים Parim are taken out in order to be...
let’s make this כשר kosher and this atone. Okay, this is מכשיר
מצווה, machshir mitzvah, we're preparing the מצווה, mitzvah, and this is an
atonement in both
cases. ושוחטי חוץ, v’shochatei chutz, I also have things in common: אדם,
Adam, I'm talking about a person doing it; חוטא, chotei, sinning, this
one transgressed, this one is doing something wrong, he's doing his sacrifice
outside the place; נשמה, neshamah, the soul is being taken. Here it's
a cow, here it's a person, here it's the שחיטה shechitah itself.
And פיגול pigul is like it's a תועבה. toeivah. It's not gonna
go. Look at the beautiful colors. The green is gonna be okay,
the red is not gonna be okay. You missed the whole show
now! Alright. Just continue stay focused, come. One zero. Alright, alright. Okay.
The answer is you need the next slide. Oh, Joe, it's not
in this anymore, you need the next one. Oh, I'll take home.
Yeah, and bring the next one. Okay. But we're almost done. We're
at the bottom of מב Mem Beis and at the bottom of
the hour, at the bottom of the ninth inning. Okay.
We could have thought that those, four for here, four for here.
The גמרא gives us an answer: מכשיר ממכשיר עדיף. machshir mi’machshir adif.
Something that makes something כשר kosher or atones for something is better
than something that is similar in the sin. Like if two of
us are doing a transgression, that would not be a place to
learn from each other how to do things better. We have to
go to the place that has a הכשר, hechsheir, that does a
מצווה mitzvah to benefit, that atones for sins. ושוחטי חוץ v’shochatei chutz
is something that should not have happened. The sacrifice is here, mistake
should be here, mistakenly they do it מחוץ למחנה. We can't learn
from a transgression how to how to do it right. Yay. Okay.
רב
פפא אמר, Rav Pappa amar, רגע, rega, now, this is what I
said you the rabbis have always in the back of their mind
because while they're having this whole conversation behind us, there's another thing
that they can count, the fact that the בית הסקילה is outside
the camp. רב
פפא אמר, Rav Pappa amar, משה, היכא הוה יתיב? Moshe heicha havah
yasiv? Where was משה Moshe, sitting? When השם Hashem says to משה,
Moshe הוצא את המקלל, hotzei es ha’Mekalel, take out the guy who's
cursing, right, outside the camp, where is משה Moshe, sitting? משה Moshe
is sitting in מחנה לוייה Machaneh Leviyah in the second camp, not
inside קודש הקודשים Kodesh HaKodashim when this conversation happens. משה Moshe is
sitting in מחנה לוייה. Machaneh Leviyah. When השם Hashem says to הוצא
hotzei and מחוץ למחנה, we're out one camp. And then what happened?
Right? So, okay, wait. משה Moshe
היכא הוה יתיב? heicha havah yasiv? Where is he sitting? במחנה לוייה.
B’machaneh Leviyah. ואמר ליה רחמנא, v’amar lei Rachmana, הוצא את המקלל אל
מחוץ למחנה. Take out the cursing guy outside the camp. מחוץ למחנה
לוייה, m’chutz l’machaneh Leviyah, one. And then the פסוק continues and says,
ויוציאו את המקלל אל מחוץ למחנה. vayotziu es ha’Mekalel el m’chutz lamachaneh.
They took out the cursing guy outside the camp. But he's already
outside. If that was sufficient, they would not have had to take
him out one more camp. מחוץ למחנה ישראל. m’chutz l’machaneh Yisrael. הא
מיבעי ליה לעשייה? ha miba’ei lei la’asiyah? Are you sure this is
how it was done? עשייה בהדיא כתיבא, asiyah b’hedya kesivah, ובני ישראל
עשו כאשר צוה השם את משה. uvnei Yisrael asu ka’asher tzivah Hashem
es Moshe.
In that same encounter of the מקלל, it is said the children
of Israel did exactly what השם Hashem commanded משה. Moshe. I.e., בית
הסקילה is outside all the camps, not inside our dwelling place. This
is where the execution site is. Even if the בית דין happens
to be outside the camp, that בית הסקילה still has to be
farther. And with that, we're at the top of מג Mem Gimmel
for tomorrow. Thank you very much for learning with us this morning
and a wonderful week, שבוע טוב. Shavua Tov.